Barnersville Estate

Monrovia, Liberia

October 22, 2022

Dr. Susanne Schilling
Lecturer/Assistant Professor
School of Biology and Environmental Science
University of Dublin, Ireland

Dear Dr. Susanne Schilling,

In response to the scholarship advertised by your institution, I write to apply for this once in a lifetime opportunity. I hold a Bachelor of Science degree in Plant and Soil Science from Cuttington University.

I reckon I am a great fit for this position and your group because I have performed similar responsibilities while I worked as a volunteer at the Central Agricultural Research Institute. I was a part of a team involved with the identification of favorable phenotypic traits for rice breeding. I also have a vast knowledge and experience in crop cultivation and management.

Additionally, my research and data collection, analysis and visualization skills are worthwhile. I believe these skills highly connect to the core responsibilities of the position. Research is a tedious process and is sometimes frustrating. I am a resilient individual who never gives up. I strive to always finish what I have started, and I motivate myself to do so.

I also have a background in Python Programming. Programming has enhanced my critical thinking and problem-solving skills to a considerable extent. Thus, I rest assure that these skills will be very useful to perform the responsibilities of the position. Bioinformatics is highly useful nowadays in plant improvement and programming is an essential piece. My programming skills can be useful in data collection, storage, manipulation, and dissemination during the research process.

My curriculum vitae is attached for more details. Hope to hear from you soon.

Respectfully Yours,

Americ Allison

## **Curriculum Vitae of Americ Allison**

Email: americ474@gmail.com

Cell #s: +231-775178202/+231-880832727

Address: Barnersville Estate, Montserrado County, Liberia

#### **EDUCATION**

# Bachelor of Science (B.Sc.), Plant and Soil Science | July 2016

**Minor: Accounting** 

Cuttington University, Suakoko, Bong County, Liberia

## **High School Diploma** | June 2012

Sister Shirley Kolmer Memorial Catholic School

Barnersville Estate, Montserrado County, Liberia

### **WORK EXPERIENCE**

## **IT Mentor**

Institute of Basic Technology, 72<sup>nd</sup>, Montserrado County | February 2022 - present

- teaches computer literacy and basic Python Programming
- mentors students on IT related issues
- automates basic tasks with Python and MS Excel

#### Volunteer

AfricaRice DeSIRA-IRFFS, Suakoko, Bong County | April 2021 – July 2021

- assisted the Monitoring, Evaluation and Learning Specialist with data analysis
- partook in sowing of rice and field research

## **Resource Room Assistant**

Cuttington University, Suakoko, Bong County | December 2016 - January 2021

- assist students and faculty with research and data analysis
- scan documents for faculty and students
- ensure books are properly shelved according to their call numbers and Resource Room policies are always followed

# Algebra Teacher

Calvary Baptist Church School System, Suakoko, Bong County | September 18, 2017 – September 6, 2018

- prepared lesson plans in line with the national curriculum and taught algebraic concepts
- motivated students and maintained discipline in the classroom; served as a role model
- evaluated student progress

Volunteer (Teaching Assistant, Urbanization and Sustainable Development)
College of Agriculture and Sustainable Development (Cuttington University) Suakoko, Bong
County | September 11, 2017- December 8, 2017

- corrected students' assignments
- monitored students who were assigned by the lecturer to read in the Resource Room
- lectured students when the instructor was absent

## Volunteer

Central Agricultural Research Institute (CARI), Suakoko, Bong County | July 2017 - August 2017

- participated in rice nursery preparation and identification of phenotypic traits for breeding
- participated in transplanting of rice seedlings and data collection

## **Agriculture Intern**

College of Agriculture and Sustainable Development Farm (Cuttington University), Suakoko, Bong County | July 2016 - August 2016

- assisted in vegetable nursery preparation
- assisted in field layout for vegetable cultivation
- assisted in sowing and management of vegetables

Volunteer (Teaching Assistant, Experimental Design and Statistics)
College of Agriculture and Sustainable Development (Cuttington University) Suakoko, Bong
County | November 2015 - February 2016

- assisted students in using Microsoft Excel in the statistics lab
- tutored students

#### **ACHIEVEMENTS**

Certificate of Completion (Introduction to Python Programming-Flask Framework)
Monrovia Meetup Computer Science Academy, Orange Digital Center, Montserrado County,
Liberia - February 2022 – July 2022

Certificate of Recognition (2<sup>nd</sup> Best Project)

Monrovia Meetup Computer Science Academy, Orange Digital Center, Montserrado County, Liberia - July 2022

Certificate of Excellence (First Class Honors Graduate) Cuttington University, Suakoko, Bong County - July 2016

**Certificate of Completion** (Introduction to Information Technology) **Alison - Free Online Learning -** 2016

## **SKILLS**

**Technical**: Can work in Microsoft Office and use internet and emails; can type about 30 words per minute; knowledgeable on Python Programming (Numpy, Pandas, Matplotlib, Flask), R, Experimental Research, Data Collection, Analysis and Visualization

Language: English: EF Standard English Test 73 (Proficient) – <a href="https://www.efset.org/cert/WYQXQq">www.efset.org/cert/WYQXQq</a>

Other skills: Can complete challenging tasks in time and learn very quickly; can work both independently and in a team; punctual; flexible; self-motivated; good communicator

## **ACADEMIC REFEREES**

1. Dr. Dennis W. Eaton (*PhD*)

IP Consult, Ethiopia, Agricultural TVET Consultant

Email: <a href="mailto:dwe03601@gmail.com">dwe03601@gmail.com</a>
Facebook: W Dennis Eaton
WhatsApp: +251989022218

2. Mr. Jacob B. Kolleh (BSc., PGDE, M.Phil.)

Central Agricultural Research Institute, Liberia

Research Officer & Head, Department of Socio-economics and Applied Statistics

Email: jbkolleh@gmail.com

3. Mr. J. Lepolu Torlon

AfricaRice DeSIRA-IRFFS

Monitoring and Evaluation Learning Specialist

Phone: +231775318131

Email: lepolu1975@gmail.com

# Cuttington University

To All Who May Read These Letters Greetings
By Authority of the Board of Trustees of
Cuttington University
and upon the recommendation of the faculty

# Americ Allison

has been admitted to the degree of Bachelor of Science in Plant and Soil Science

and is entitled to all the rights and honors thereto appertaining Witness the seal of the University and the signatures of its officers Given at Suakoko Gbarnga Liberia this 30<sup>th</sup> day of July Two Thousand and Sixteen

President of the Bealif of Trustees

Secretary of the Board of Trustees

TON UNITED STATES

Certificate No.

SEKandekai

Theodore VK Brown, So